Register of the William Loren McGonagle papers
Hoover Institution Archives
William Loren McGonagle papers
1947-1999
99046
McGonagle, William Loren
10 manuscript boxes (4.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The William L. McGonagle collection describes the devastation caused by the Israeli naval and air attack on the American naval intelligence ship Liberty on June 8, 1967, and the honors and citations bestowed on him for heroism and sacrifice. Materials include correspondence, reports, orders, personnel records, writings, printed matter, and photographs
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research. Access to audiovisual materials requires at least two weeks advance notice. Audiovisual materials include sound recordings, video recordings, and motion picture film. Hoover staff will determine whether use copies of the materials requested can be made available. Some materials may not be accessible even with advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1999
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http: //library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1925 Nov. 19 Born, Wichita, Kansas
1942 Sept. - 1944 June Graduated, Coachella Valley Union High School, Indio, California
1944 July - 1945 Nov. Student, University of Redlands, Redlands, California
1947 June A.B. in History, University of Southern California, Los Angeles, California
1947-1950 Served in the destroyer USS Frank Knox and minesweeper USS Partridge and served in the minesweeper USS Kite during the Korean War
1947 June Commissioned, in the rank of Ensign
1951 Sept. - Dec. U.S. Naval School (Electronics), San Francisco, California
1952 Jan. - 1953 July U.S. Naval Advance Base, Bremerhaven, Germany
1959 Jan. - 1961 June Assistant Professor of Naval Science, Naval Weapons, Leadership, and Naval Operations
1959 June - 1961 June B.S. in Education, University of Idaho, Moscow, Idaho
1963 July 1 Promoted to Commander
1966 April - 1967 Sept. Commanding Officer of the technical research ship USS Liberty
1967 June 8 Israeli naval and air attack on the American naval intelligence ship USS Liberty; Received Purple Heart and Medal of Honor
1967 Oct. Promoted to the rank of Captain, Commanded the new ammunition ship Kilauea Led the NROTC Unit at the University of Oklahoma
1969 Aug. - 1971 May Commanding Officer and Professor of Naval Science, Chief Navy Division Awarded meritorious Service Medal (Gold Star in lieu of Award)
1974 Aug. 1 Retired from active duty
1999 Mar. 3 Died, Palm Springs, California
Scope and Content of Collection
The William McGonagle papers narrate the story of the Israeli naval and air attack on the American naval intelligence ship USS Liberty on June 8, 1967. Materials consist of correspondence, reports, orders, personnel records, writings, printed matter, and photographs relating to the incident.
The central theme of the papers is the incident on USS Liberty. The surprise Israeli attack on the U.S. ship, the damages on the ship, loss of lives, and serious injuries produced an outcry all over the world. The heroic effort made by William McGonagle to save his shipmates earned him the Medal of Honor and citations as well as the respect of the United States Navy and beyond.
The United States Navy File contains general information about the Navy and William McGonagle's personal files. The files record William McGonagle's assignments, including the USS Liberty, USS Kilauea, and JUSMAG Philippines. The USS Liberty records include numerous photographs which present a picture of the destruction and injuries.
In addition, there are two 1/4-inch sound tape reels that contain information about the USS Liberty and an interview.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 4 series: Biographical File, United States Navy File, Photographs and Negatives, and 1/4-Inch Sound Tape Reel
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Liberty (Ship); Israel-Arab War, 1967--Naval operations.; United States--Armed forces--Mediterranean Sea.; United States--Foreign relations--Israel.; Israel--Foreign relations--United States.; United States. Navy-Officers.
Collection Contents
- Biographical File, 1960-1999 and undated (Box 1-2)
  Citations, clippings, correspondence with the next of kin of men who died under his command, identification cards, memoranda, notice of discharge from active duty, personal files, printed matter, and speaking file, as well as books and papers written by others presented to William McGonagle. Arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Biographical information, 1960 and undated. (Folder 1: 1)
    Includes photographs of William McGonagle
  - Citations, undated (Folder 1: 2)
  - Clippings, 1968-1999 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1993. (Folder 1: 4)
    Letters and addresses for the next of kin of men who died under his command. Includes photographs of Marines, undated
  - Geneva Convention identification cards, undated (Folder 1: 5)
  - Memorandum for record about an interview with Kathryn Hatch, Newsweek, 1969 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Notice of discharge from duty, 1974 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Personal files, 1969-1982 and undated (Folder 1: 8-10)
  - Printed matter, 1969 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Speaking file, 1969-1971 (Folder 1: 12)
    - United States of America's Congressional Medal of Honor Recipients and Their Official Citations, copyrights held by Highland Publishers and Highland House II, 1980 and 1994 (Folder 1: 13)
    - The USS Liberty: Dissenting History VS. Official History, John E. Borne, 1995 (Folder 2: 1)
    - The Liberty Incident, a dissertation by A. Jay Kristol, University of Miami, 1997 (Folder 2: 2-3)
  - Miscellany, 1966-1998 and undated (Folder 2: 4)
- United States Navy File, 1948-1998 and undated. (Box 2-8)
  Correspondence, fitness reports of officers, publicity file, and scrapbook, arranged alphabetically by physical form. The records of ships, especially the USS Liberty, are described separately in the same order
  - William McGonagle office files
    - 1952-1969 and undated (Folder 2: 5-6)
    - 1963-1969 (Folder 3: 1-2)
  - Correspondence
    - 1968 (Folder 3: 3)
      Includes photographic prints of William McGonagle and others,undated
    - 1969-1991 (Folder 3: 4)
    - 1970 and undated (Folder 3: 5)
    - 1970-1990 (Folder 3: 6)
    - 1986-1992 (Folder 3: 7)
    - 1991 (Folder 3: 8)
      - Secretary of the Navy
    - 1992 (Folder 3: 9)
  - Fitness reports, 1948-1973 (Folder 3: 10-12)
  - Instruction sheets and list of crew members, undated (Folder 4: 1)
  - Memoranda, 1948-1987 (Folder 4: 2-4)
  - Note, undated (Folder 4: 5)
  - Printed matter, 1968-1970 (Folder 4: 6)
  - Publicity file, 1968-1969 (Folder 4: 7)
  - Scrapbook - The Keel: United States Naval Training Center, Great Lakes, Illinois, undated (Folder 4: 8)
  - JUSMAG Philippines, 1969-1984. (Folder 4: 9-10)
    Includes officers' evaluation and fitness reports
  - USS Kilauea
    - Correspondence, 1969 (Folder 5: 1)
    - Fitness reports of officers, 1967-1970 (Folder 5: 2)
    - Newsclip file, 1967-1968. (Folder 5: 3)
      Includes a photograph of William McGonagle and Navy personnel,undated
    - Press kit, 1968 (Folder 5: 4)
    - Press releases, 1967-1971. (Folder 5: 5)
      Includes photographs of William McGonagle and others,undated
    - Printed matter, 1968 (Folder 5: 6)
      Includes photographs depicting William McGonagle and others, undated
    - Miscellany, undated (Folder 5: 7)
  - USS Liberty
    - General, 1967-1968 (Folder 5: 8)
    - Awards and Chief Naval Officer's letter authorizing awards, 1991 and undated (Folder 5: 9)
    - Basic orders and endorsements, 1967-1968 (Folder 5: 10)
    - Casualty records, 1967 (Folder 5: 11)
    - Clippings and media coverage, 1967-1998 and undated (Folder 6: 1-3)
      - 1966-1967 and undated (Folder 6: 4)
      - 1967-1984 (Folder 6: 5)
      - 1978-1988 (Folder 6: 6)
      - 1981-1988 (Folder 7: 1)
      - 1990-1991 (Folder 7: 2)
      - 1994 (Folder 7: 3)
    - Court of enquiry, 1967 (Folder 7: 4)
    - Fitness reports, 1967-1980 (Folder 7: 5-6)
    - Lists (Folder 7:)
    - Honors, undated (Folder 7: 7)
    - Materials, 1992-1998 (Folder 7: 8)
    - Navy/Marine Corps/Civilian personnel killed or died as a result of combat action during the armed attack on USS Liberty, 1967 (Folder 7: 9)
    - Survivors, undated (Folder 7: 10)
    - Medical file, 1968 and undated (Folder 7: 11)
    - Memoranda, 1967-1971 (Folder 7: 12)
    - Memorial service, 1993 (Folder 7: 13)
      Includes photographs of memorial tombs,undated
    - Newsletters, 1981-1996 (Folder 8: 1-2)
    - Note, 1967 (Folder 8: 3)
    - Press release, 1966-1967 (Folder 8: 4)
    - Printed matter, 1967-1998 (Folder 8: 5-6)
    - Program, 1965-1966 (Folder 8: 7)
    - Schedule, 1982 (Folder 8: 8)
    - Statements, 1991-1998 (Folder 8: 9)
    - Summary of events, undated (Folder 8: 10)
    - Telegram, 1967 (Folder 8: 11)
    - Writings by others, 1967 (Folder 8: 12)
    - Miscellany, 1964-1971 (Folder 8: 13)
  - Telegrams, 1967 (Folder 8: 14)
  - Miscellany, 1967-1971 and undated (Folder 8: 15)
- Photographs and Negatives, 1967-1973 and undated (Box 9-10)
  Photographs and negatives depicting William McGonagle and others arranged in groups, as well as images of the USS Liberty and USS Kilauea
  - Unidentified, undated (Folder 9: 1)
  - William McGonagle, undated. (Folder 9: 2)
  - Collection of photographs, undated (Folder 9: 3)
  - USS Kilauea (Folder 9:)
    - Commissioning photographs, 1968 and undated (Folder 9: 4-5)
    - William McGonagle and others watching Commissary man involved in the preparation of the commissioning of the USS Kilauea, undated. (Folder 9: 6-7)
      Includes Kiwanis Club and Sogibow, Michigan, 1970
  - USS Liberty (Folder 9:)
    - Commanding officers, USS Liberty, undated (Folder 9: 8)
    - Awards presentation on the USS Liberty, undated. (Folder 9: 9)
      Includes related materials, undated
    - Album, Photographs of the USS Liberty, circa 1967 (Folder 9: 10)
    - Photographs of the USS Liberty with William McGonagle on board, 1967 (Folder 9: 11)
  - Salvage photographs - Guam, 1962 (Folder 10: 1)
  - Bronze Star Medal award, 1968 (Folder 10: 2)
  - Album of Navy Division building and signing of lease for Phil Navy Ship YD-205, 1973 (Folder 10: 3)
  - Negatives, undated (Folder 10: 4)
- 1/4-Inch Sound Tape Reels, 1967-1969. (Box 10)
  Consists of recordings of a USS Liberty press conference and an unidentified interview
  - USS Liberty press conference tape, 1967 (Folder 10: 5)
  - WKY radio interview, 1969 (Folder 10: 6)